Feinstein International Center Records UA197
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- White papers, UA197.000267
  - Uganda: Upholding Rights in the Face of Violence, 2001 -- 2012; UA197.004; 14 Digital Object(s)
    - Adaptation and Resilience: Responses to Changing Dynamics in Northern Karamoja, Uganda, 2010-11-19; UA197.004.004.00013; Stites, Elizabeth; Huisman, Carrie Stefansky
      This briefing paper is the first output from the LIVE project (Livelihoods, Insecurity and Value Chains Examination in Karamoja), a collaborative study with Save the Children in Uganda funded by USAID Food for Peace. Based on fieldwork from August 2010, the paper examines livelihoods, food security, and security in the northern Karamoja districts of Kotido and Kaabong, and seeks to understand the livelihood adaptations of communities and households to recent changes caused by internal stresses and external shocks. The briefing paper also examines community perspectives on new food aid policies, and discusses possible gaps between local and external expectations and program goals.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Food security; Human Security; Feinstein International Center
    - Tradition in Transition: Customary Authority in Karamoja, Uganda, 2012-11-01; UA197.004.004.00014; Carlson, Khristopher; Proctor, Keith; Stites, Elizabeth; Akabwai, Darlington; Customary authority in the Karamoja region of Uganda has undergone profound shifts in parallel to the changing livelihoods and security conditions in the region over the past several decades. This study, funded by Irish Aid Kampala, examines the evolution of customary authority among four population groups, the Jie, Dodoth, Matheniko and Tepeth. Overall the study finds that customary mechanisms have been slow to adapt to the changes in the region and have seen decreased influence over the day-to-day legal, economic, diplomatic and ritual affairs of local communities
      Uganda; Karamoja Province (Uganda); Customary law; Economies and societies in transition; Feinstein International Center
  - Darfur: Livelihoods, Vulnerability, and Choice, 2005 -- 2012; UA197.005; 10 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Darfur: Livelihoods, vulnerability, and choice project.
    - Adaptation and Devastation: The Impact of the Conflict on Trade and Markets in Darfur, 2008; UA197.005.005.00001; Buchanan-Smith, Margie; Fadul, Abduljabbar Abdulla
      Conflict and crisis in Darfur has continued unabated since 2003. Whilst there has been a growing body of knowledge about how this has impacted on livelihoods, there has been much less focus on understanding how trade and markets - the lifeblood of Darfur's economy - have been affected. This report begins to address this gap between livelihoods research and the crisis' effects on trade and markets.
    - Livelihoods, Power, and Choice: The Vulnerability of the Northern Rizaygat, Darfur, Sudan, 2009-01-24; UA197.005.005.00002; Young, Helen; Osman, Abdal Monium; Abusin, Ahmed Malik; Asher, Michael; Egemi, Omer
      Based on fieldwork in rural Darfur, this report uses a livelihoods lens to illustrate the processes that have contributed to the vulnerability of the Darfuri nomads who have much in common with pastoralists globally. Severe pressures on pastoralist livelihoods have contributed to 'maladaptive' livelihood strategies that are often linked to violence and Conflict, Armed (War), and undermine the livelihoods of both victims and perpetrators.
      Economies and societies in transition; Human beings--Migrations; Conflict, Armed (War); Feinstein International Center
    - Livelihoods, Migration and Conflict: Discussion of Findings from Two Studies in West and North Darfur, 2006 - 2007, 2009-06-09; UA197.005.005.00003; Young, Helen; Jacobsen, Karen; Osman, Abdal Monim
      This briefing paper discusses findings from a study conducted in Darfur from 2006-8 that explored the changing role of Human beings--Migrations and remittances in the livelihoods of Conflict, Armed (War)-affected people.
    - Responding to Violence in Ikotos County, South Sudan: Government and Local Efforts to Restore Order, 2008-01-28; UA197.005.005.00004; Ochan, Clement
      This report from an understudied area details the effects of and responses to violence in Ikotos County in Eastern Equatoria in Southern Sudan. The author, from Southern Sudan himself, draws upon five years of experience, observation and interviews in Ikotos and supplements this information with data from interviews with local officials and community groups.
    - Review of WFP Food Assistance Programming Practices in Southern Sudan, 2006-10-13; UA197.005.005.00005; Maxwell, Daniel; Sim, Amanda; Mutonyi, Mercy
      The World Food Programme has been providing humanitarian food assistance to vulnerable communities and groups in Southern Sudan for over twenty years, but circumstances have changed following the signing of the Comprehensive Peace Agreement (CPA) in January 2005. The Feinstein International Center undertook this review of programs in Southern Sudan to help WFP Sudan make the needed changes to adapt to these new circumstances. The objective of this study is to improve programming in the 2007 EMOP and the subsequent PRRO. The Feinstein International Center views this as one step to building a long-term partnership with WFP Sudan.
      Nutrition; Food security; Feinstein International Center
    - Strategies for Economic Recovery and Peace In Darfur, 2007-07-30; UA197.005.005.00006; Young, Helen; Osman, Abdal Monium; Dale, Rebecca
      Competing livelihoods in the absence of good local governance has led to localized and ultimately devastating Conflict, Armed (War) over natural resources in Darfur. The lack of comprehensive livelihoods analysis in international peace processes and humanitarian assistance risks entrenching the Darfur Conflict, Armed (War) even further. Livelihoods analysis is a prerequisite for ensuring that resources are allocated according to need between competing livelihood groups i.e. impartiality of humanitarian response, and for appropriate planning/implementation of future recovery and development. To date, the humanitarian response has favoured certain groups while marginalizing others, specifically the Abbala arabs. Based upon intensive field research and consultation, this briefing note explains the background to the livelihoods and economic crisis in the Darfur region, and lays out specific recommendations for how it can be addressed.
      Peace-building; Economic recovery in Africa; Feinstein International Center
    - Darfur: Livelihoods Under Seige, 2005-07-08; UA197.005.005.00007; Young, Helen; Osman, Abdul Monim; Aklilu, Yacob; Dale, Rebecca; Badri, Babiker; Fuddle, Abdul Jabbar Abdullah
      It is almost two years since the beginning of the rebel insurgency in Darfur, but the Conflict, Armed (War) continues, the ceasefire has been frequently violated, and the world's worst humanitarian crisis continues to deepen. At the last estimate, more than 1.6 million people had been displaced as a result of system­atic attacks on villages, with associated violence, killings, burning of homes, looting of Livestock, and theft and destruction of material assets.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Refugees; Forced migration; Feinstein International Center
    - Guidance Document on the World Food Programme, 2006-07-17; UA197.005.005.00008; Feinstein International Center
      This document has been prepared as part of the World Food Programme (WFP) Sudan's Food Aid Forum held from June 6-9 2006, in Khartoum, Sudan. The purpose of the document is threefold: 1. To inform those who did not attend the Forum on its content and outcome 2. To serve as an outcome document for those who did attend 3. To be a tool for WFP in their strategic planning process.
      Food relief; Food security; Feinstein International Center
    - Navigating Without a Compass: The Erosion of Humanitarianism in Darfur, 2011-01-24; UA197.005.005.00009; Feinstein International Center
      Over the past seven years, the conflict in the Darfur region of Sudan has changed and humanitarian needs and response have evolved. The particular developments since the expulsion of the 13 INGOs and the revoking of the licenses of the national NGOs by the government of Sudan in 2009 have largely gone uncharted and unremarked. This discussion paper explores the challenges facing current humanitarian action that are linked with the ongoing conflict in the region; the floundering peace process; the exponential decline in security; the NGO expulsions linked with the indictment of President al-Bashir by the International Criminal Court; and the wider government strategy on Darfur.
    - Trade and Market Bulletin North Darfur, 2011-06-23; UA197.005.005.00010; Young, Helen
      The Feinstein International Center provides advisory support to the Darfur Development and Reconstruction Agency (DRA) a national NGO in Sudan to set up and manage a community-based market monitoring network in the Darfur Region. The goal of this market monitoring initiative is to deepen analysis and understanding of the shifting patterns of trade and markets in Darfur on an ongoing basis for key agricultural and livestock commodities; identify how livelihoods and the economy can be supported through trade; and identify peace-building opportunities through trade. Seven community-based organizations (CBOs) plus DRA are monitoring 15 markets across North Darfur, including three markets in IDP camps, on a weekly basis. A new CBO-based market monitoring network is currently being established in West Darfur and eventually the network will be extended to cover all of the Darfur Region.
      Volume, issue
      1, 1
      Livelihood Obstacles; Feinstein International Center
    - Trade and Market Bulletin North Darfur, 2011-07-26; UA197.005.005.00011; Young, Helen
      1, 2
    - Trade and Market Bulletin North Darfur, 2011-11-16; UA197.005.005.00012; Young, Helen
      1, 3
    - Trade and Market Bulletin North Darfur, 2012-02-15; UA197.005.005.00013; Young, Helen
      1, 4
    - On the Hoof: Livestock Trade in Darfur, 2012-09-01; UA197.005.005.00014; Buchanan-Smith, Margie; Fadul, Abdul Jabbar Abdulla; Tahir, Abdul Rahman; Akilu, Yacob; This report explores what has happened to the livestock trade in the greater Darfur region during nine years of conflict, since 2003. Livestock is one of Darfur's main economic assets and makes a major contribution to Sudan's national livestock and meat exports. The report documents how Darfur's livestock trade has been negatively affected by the conflict, contracting in volume and losing competitiveness as trading costs have soared and as the quality of animals brought to the market has deteriorated.
      Sudan; Darfur; Livestock; Feinstein International Center
  - Crisis and Social Transformation in Nepal, 2009 -- 2010; UA197.006; 2 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Crisis and Social Transformation in Nepal project.
    - Aid and Violence: Development Policies and Conflict in Nepal, 2009; UA197.006.006.00001; Bonino, Francesca; Donini, Antonio
      The Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist) launched its "People's War" in 1996. The Maoists' rise to power was impressive by any standard. After a successful showing at the polls for the Constituent Assembly in April 2008, they became the strongest organized political force in the country. At the same time, foreign aid has been a fixture of Nepal's development efforts since the 1950s: the donor community has been the key partner in Nepal's development successes and failures. How did these two realitiesthe insurgency and foreign aidinteract? The report explores this question through a retrospective analysis of the development/conflict nexus in Nepal. It looks at the underlying causes of the Maoist success story, in relation to the conditions of structural underdevelopment and violence, and at donors' policies and activities in Nepal and at their interplay with the conflict environment. The report focuses on the last decade (1996-2008), the period of the Maoist insurgency and of the subsequent largely successful peace process. It looks at the way in which aid actors in Nepal framed their understanding of the Maoist insurgency and at how they adapted their responses. It shows that, because the aid community was Kathmandu-centric, it did not fully grasp the nature of caste, class and ethnic discrimination in rural Nepal nor that "development" was not benefiting the most disadvantaged groups. Development failure can thus be construed as a contributing factor to the insurgency.
      Humanitarian aid; Feinstein International Center
    - Towards a "Great Transformation"?: The Maoist Insurgency and Local Perceptions of Social Transformation in Nepal, 2010-07-27; UA197.006.006.00002; Sharma, Jeevan Raj; Donini, Antonio
      This report presents the findings of a two-year field research project on local perceptions of social transformation in rural Nepal. The findings, and our interpretations of them, are presented in a manner that can contribute not only to scholarly debate but also to current discussions on development policy choices and on the role of aid agencies. Our study shows that alongside the political transition, there is clear evidence of a qualitative "step-change" in the way Nepali society is organized that is beyond the continual or "normal" processes of incremental change that are always at work. Field evidence clearly suggests that many existing social norms and patterns are being challenged and are being reconstructed.
  - Preparing for Humanitarian Crises of the Future, 2004 -- 2010; UA197.007; 10 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Preparing for Humanitarian Crises of the Future project.
    - Ambiguity and Change: Humanitarian NGOs Prepare for the Future, 2009; UA197.007.007.00001; Donini, Antonio; Borrel, Annalies; Kent, Randolph; Minear, Larry; Moomaw, William; Mowjee, Tasneem; Najam, Adil; Purdin, Susan; Walker, Peter; Wisner, Ben
      This study provides international NGOs with a rudimentary framework for strategic planning in the light of the likely challenges of ambiguity and change awaiting them during the next decade. It examines a series of hazard domains environment, urbanization, migration, and HIV/AIDS within which NGOs can exercise at least a modicum of control. It identifies other variables well beyond the capacity of NGOs to manage, including combinations of crises that cut across these individual domains and, more broadly still, civilization-changing events.
      Humanitarian aid; Policy; Feinstein International Center
    - The Humanitarian Costs of Climate Change, 2009-02-06; UA197.007.007.00002; Webster, Mackinnon; Ginnetti, Justin; Walker, Peter; Coppard, Daniel; Kent, Randolph
      Using existing international databases that track disaster occurrence and humanitarian costs, this research attempts to improve understanding of how climate change may affect international humanitarian spending.
      Climate Change; Feinstein International Center
    - Impact Assessment of Humanitarian Response, 2008-10-06; UA197.007.007.00003; Watson, Cathy
      This Review summarizes current thinking on Impact assessment in humanitarian assistance, and considers how recent field based initiatives have addressed some of the key issues and challenges facing Impact assessment in the sector. Part one of the review presents a summary of the literature on Impact assessment, focusing on Impact assessment of humanitarian assistance and highlighting the key issues and challenges. These are presented in terms of Conceptual Issues; Methodological Issues; and Organizational Issues. Part two then considers the development of the Participatory Impact Assessment (PIA) methodology by the Feinstein International Center and its application, and the extent to which the challenges outlined in Part one have been addressed by these and other recent developments.
    - One for All and All for One: Support and Assistance Models for an Effective IFRC, 2004-08-04; UA197.007.007.00004; Walker, Peter; Minear, Larry
      In recent years and for a variety of reasons, the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies (IFRC) has been buffeted by an array of forces. In one sense, the pressures are similar to those experienced by other federations, perhaps accentuated by the fact that the IFRC is one of the earliest and developed into the largest such federated, or federal, institutions. Like other federations, the IFRC is struggling with a set of generic problems. These include being a faithful representative at the global level of diverse national member societies and needs; promoting coordination of members which often comes with a great temptation to directly implement projects; and finding a workable balance between the federalism of the past and the increasingly profile-conscious bilateral and unilateral actions of its membership. The Federation has also been faced with managing the increasingly intense competition within the humanitarian sector which involves traditional humanitarian actors but now also for-profit entrepreneurs and military forces engaged in civic action work.
    - One for All and All for One: Intra-Organizational Dynamics in Humanitarian Action, 2009-05-29; UA197.007.007.00005; Webster, Mackinnon; Walker, Peter
      A significant proportion of humanitarian assistance is now delivered by NGOs which have in effect become federated trans-national organizations, alliances of members from different countries, all seeking to provide assistance in times of crisis. This report describes research carried out to better understand how these transnational bodies organize their membership, deliver and accountability systems in times of crisis.
    - Preventing Corruption in Humanitarian Assistance, 2008-07-16; UA197.007.007.00006; Maxwell, Daniel; Walker, Peter; Church, Cheyanne; Harvey, Paul; Savage, Kevin; Bailey, Sarah; Hees, Roslyn; Ahlendorf, Marie-Luise
      Leaders in the humanitarian community have resolved to do more to address the risks of corruption in relief efforts. Preventing Corruption in Humanitarian Assistance documents perceptions of corruption in humanitarian operations through interviews with staff of several leading international humanitarian NGOs. The study was commissioned by Transparency International (TI) and conducted jointly by the Feinstein International Center, the Humanitarian Policy Group at the Overseas Development Institute in London, and TI.
    - Professionalising the Humanitarian Sector: A Scoping Study, 2010-06-17; UA197.007.007.00007; Walker, Peter; Russ, Catherine
      This study, commissioned by the UK's Enhancing Learning and Research for Humanitarian Assistance project (ELRHA) and carried out by the Feinstein International Center in collaboration with RedR, comes after a decade in which the humanitarian enterprise has sought to develop global standards, codes and representative bodies, and amid increasing momentum for creating a global system for professional development, accreditation and association. The study explores the nature of professionalism today and sets out key recommendations which, if implemented, could increase accountability, raise the quality and consistency of humanitarian service, open up the profession to talented new recruits, and raise the status of the humanitarian service provider to a level on a par with other professional groups.
    - The Future of Humanitarian Action, 2006-08-31; UA197.007.007.00008; Walker, Peter
      While Humanitarian assistance and international disaster response have long traditions in terms of the actions of the International Red Cross and Red Crescent and a number of Christian charitable organizations (and of course, the coping mechanisms of societies and communities), humanitarianism in its present form really dates from the end of World War II. The construction of the notion of an international community of humanitarian actors (UN agencies, Red Cross/Crescent, and NGOs) grew alongside the development of the United Nations system, the Bretton Woods institutions, and the retreating of the European imperial powers and was reinforced with the ending of the Cold War.
    - Disaster globalization: Evaluating the impact of tsunami aid, 2005-07-21; UA197.007.007.00009; Walker, Peter
      The tsunami and earthquakes that hit the Indian Ocean 26th December 2004 caused a disaster so extreme and so unusual that it pushed all our models of response to the limit.
      Natural disaster; Feinstein International Center
    - Follow the Money: A Review and Analysis of the State of Humanitarian Funding, 2007-07-21; UA197.007.007.00010; Walker, Peter; Pepper, Kevin
      This briefing paper is about the financing of Humanitarian assistance. In the paper, and in the forthcoming workshop, we want to ask some basic questions.
  - Refugees and Forced Migration, 2001 -- 2012; UA197.008; 23 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Refugees and Forced Migration project.
    - Internal Displacement to Urban Areas: the Tufts-IDMC Profiling Study (Abidjan, Cote D'Ivoire), 2008-08-27; UA197.008.008.00001; Jacobsen, Karen
      After a series of political crises, Cote d'Ivoire's armed Conflict, Armed (War) erupted in 2002, leading to the division of the country into government and rebel-controlled areas. Both sides committed grave human rights abuses and hundreds of thousands of civilians fl ed attacks on villages, kidnappings, and severe persecution based on ethnicity, nationality, or political opinion. Especially targeted were northern nationals and immigrants from Burkina Faso, Mali, and Niger. Many internally displaced people migrated to urban centers such as Abidjan, Grand Bassam, and Yamoussoukro, but in urban centers they were subject to government harassment, including, in Abidjan, demolition of housing and attacks. Three peace agreements brokered between 2003 and 2005 failed, but the signing of the Ouagadougou Peace Agreement in March 2007 raised hopes for a return to stability, and many IDPs have spontaneously started to return to their areas of origin.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Refugees; Feinstein International Center
    - Beyond men pikin: Improving understanding of post-Conflict, Armed (War) child fostering in Sierra Leone, 2008-04-25; UA197.008.008.00002; Gale, Lacey
      There is growing agreement that separated Children--Crimes against are best cared for in community settings, rather than in institutions. However, even in a community setting, there is a need for standards of care that allow for monitoring of Children--Crimes against's well-being. This is particularly important in countries such as Sierra Leone which is recovering from a brutal civil war and suffering from poverty, malNutrition, and limited access to adequate medical care. Since the civil war ended in Sierra Leone, child fostering—whether informal or facilitated by humanitarian agencies and the government—has become the preferred solution for the estimated 800,000+ orphaned, abandoned, and vulnerable Children--Crimes against.
    - Internal Displacement to Urban Areas: the Tufts-IDMC Profiling Study (Methods Annex), 2008-08-21; UA197.008.008.00003; Jacobsen, Karen
      The Internal Displacement to Urban Areas project took place from 2006-2008, in three urban locations: Khartoum, Sudan; Abidjan, Cote d'Ivoire; and Santa Marta, Colombia.
    - Invisible in Thailand: Tufts-International Rescue Committee Survey of Burmese Migrants in Thailand, 2008-04-25; UA197.008.008.00004; Green-Rauerhorst, Margaret; Jacobsen, Karen; Pyne, Sandee